<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>DIY</title>
 <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net"/>
 <updated>2013-11-09T08:59:54+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net</id>
 <author>
   <name>Martin Strandbygaard</name>
   <email>martin@strandbygaard.net</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Awesome, Inexpensive, Machine Tool Light</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/11/07/awesome-inexpensive-machine-tool-light"/>
   <updated>2013-11-07T07:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/11/07/awesome-inexpensive-machine-tool-light</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A high output, totally flexible, machine tool light, that costs only $50, and can be built and mounted in 15 minutes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems too good to be true, but after I have been through a number of iterations on improving lighting on my mill, that is what I ended up with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-light/20131105-011504.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I got my &lt;a href=&quot;/2010/03/26/the-sieg-sx3-has-arrived&quot;&gt;Sieg SX3&lt;/a&gt; I first mounted a small goose neck lamp with a 14W halogen reflector spot in an E14 mount. This worked fairly well, but didn&amp;#39;t quite deliver enough illumination, and the emitted infrared heat from the lamp has annoying when working close to the lamp. Also, during extended periods, the lamp became fairly hot to the touch, so care had to be exerted not to touch the lamp. In short, a decent solution but with room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up, was a small 3W LED lamp with a long goose neck. This lamp output less lumens than the first solution, but in a more tightly focused beam, and with the longer goose neck and smaller lamp head, it was easier to manoeuvre into place to provide the illumination where it was actually needed in relation to a specific cut, and avoid unwanted shadows. Given the low wattage emitted and built up heat was not an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both attempts were hastily put together to provide just some kind of illumination close to the spindle. I finally decided I needed to improve this, since I find proper illumination to make a huge difference in my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By chance I found some cool looking 10W and up LED lamps meant as work lights on tractors, trucks, ATVs, etc., and they seemed to be perfectly suited for this task:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High lumens output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Selection of flood or spot light&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sealed to IP67 to provide good protection from &amp;quot;the elements&amp;quot;. Here, that would be chips, coolant, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiency comparable to compact fluorescent lamps, which watt-to-watt is a 2x improvement over halogen bulbs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can be powered from any number of &amp;quot;wall warts&amp;quot; I already had lying around&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up, I needed a flexible way of mounting the LED lamp on the mill (and other machine tools). The goose necks from my previous attempts were not going to carry the weight of the LED lamp head, so a different solution with the same manoeuvrability was needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up with a universal magnetic stand for a dial indicator. The reach of the arm was somewhat less than I had hoped for, but other than that it seemed like the perfect solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The magnetic base provided great freedom of placement on the mill (or any other machine tool), and plenty of holding force&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The single locking mechanism on the arm, made it a comfortable two-hand operation to position the lamp head and lock it into place. No wishing for a third hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was cheap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Built&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the BOM I ended up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LED lamp ($20)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An M4 stainless cap screw bolt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two M4 washers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An M4 nut to go on the bolt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universal magnetic stand ($30)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-light/20131105-005737.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what the kit looks like put together. I opted for a flood beam LED light, because I only have a small mill and the lamp head will be mounted in close proximity to the spindle. For larger machines or other situations where the lamp head is mounted further away from the action, I would recommend a spot beam shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-light/20131105-010259.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m going to add a spot beam lamp to my setup, and move the flood lamp a little further away, to get good overall lighting of the work area, and concentrated illumination of the cutting action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to capture the level of light provided by the lamp. The dynamic range of this on-screen image is much less than what the human eye can discern, and is generally limited with the color depth of the display or print technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-light/20131105-011313.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do think this image captures the provided illumination fairly well, in relation to the overall lighting of the surroundings in my workshop, which is already very well illuminated with white walls and ceilings, and 200W of installed fluorescent overhead lighting in an area of just 12 m2.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>DRO Mount (Y-axis) on Sieg SX3</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/11/03/sx3-dro-yaxis"/>
   <updated>2013-11-03T07:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/11/03/sx3-dro-yaxis</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are many posts about DRO installation on a bench top mill. This is yet another one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post details how I installed DRO on the Y-axis of my &lt;a href=&quot;/2010/03/26/the-sieg-sx3-has-arrived&quot;&gt;Sieg SX3&lt;/a&gt;. Unlike most other builds I&amp;#39;ve seen, I elected to use magnetic tape, instead of the usual plunger- or optical scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magnetic tape and encoder has several advantages over optical scales (which in turn are better than plungers): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The magnetic tape mounted in an aluminium profile is much more robust than an optical scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both scale and encoder head are fully sealed to IP67 which makes them much more resilient to the harsh environment on a mill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The required aluminium profile and magnetic encoder head are much smaller than a comparable optical system, making them easer to fit in tight spaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I live in Denmark, the selection of readily available DRO systems is much smaller than in the states. I selected a system from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.machine-dro.co.uk&quot;&gt;Allendale Electronics Ltd.&lt;/a&gt;, and they provided excellent support on selecting suitable components for my specific mill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course this comes at a price, and a full DRO system using magnetic tape and encoders is around 20% more expensive than a comparable system using optical scales. Also, while the magnetic encoders have a resolution of 1 micron (0.001mm), their accuracy is only +/- 0.015mm whereas typical optical encoders have an accuracy of +/- 0.005mm, and this may be a deal breaker for some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I doubt the Sieg SX3 is capable of repeatedly working to such tolerances, and the temperature variations in my workshop are certainly much too great for that level of accuracy. Also, the prototypes I make usually only need to hold &amp;quot;look good&amp;quot; tolerances, typically within 0.08-0.1mm. So, I prioritised the practical benefits of a system based on magnetic encoders, and I&amp;#39;ve been very happy with it so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Installation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a dial indicator to level the aluminium profile holding the magnetic tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20130929-215311.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mounting holes in the aluminium profile was used to transfer the hole locations to the Y-axis saddle. The holes in the aluminium profile has recessed hole for the screw heads. The OD of a 13mm hole transfer punch fits perfectly in this recess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transferred holes are then drilled to Ø3.2mm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20130929-221612.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drilled holes are tapped with an M4 tap. There was no room for a tap guide, and an M4 tap is easy to snap, so I used a new taps, separate rougher, intermediate, and finisher taps, and plenty of cutting paste to prevent tap breakage. The Y-axis saddle is cast iron which is actually very easy to tap, and yields very clean and well defined threads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20130929-224526.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a test mount to check for fit of the aluminium profile. As can be seen, it has not been cut to size yet. The extrusion is mounted with M4 screws, but the pre-cut holes in the profile are Ø6mm, so they allow for plenty of play to compensate for off-centre mounting holes, and any fine adjustments to level the extrusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the Y-axis saddle as guide to scribe lines where the profile will be cut to length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20130929-225049.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the profile is cut to length, the dial indicator setup is again used to level the profile on the Y-axis saddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20130929-231440.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The profile mounted with cover holding the magnetic tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20130929-232532.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, a bracket is made, that will hold the magnetic encoder head. It is just a simple aluminium angle bracket with 4 holes. Two for mounting to the mill base, and two for holding the encoder head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20131011-113138.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bracket was used to again transfer the hole locations to the mill base using a hole punch. The angle bracket does not provide a very good guide for the hole punch, so afterwards it was necessary to shape the mounting holes in the bracket with a needle file. Slightly annoying, but it has no practical implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the holes were transferred they were drilled with Ø4.3mm and tapped using M5 rougher, intermediate, and finisher taps. The mill base cast is only about 12mm thick, so it was an easy through-hole tap, even though there wasn&amp;#39;t room for a tapping guide. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, I could easily have used a finisher tap directly, since the cast iron is very easy to cut, and a broken tap would have been easy to remove. However, I approach all modifications I make on existing (=expensive) equipment as one-shot-only, and so I take the long approach of tap forming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20131011-122756.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the bracket is mounted and the magnetic encoder head is installed on the bracket. Clearance between the encoder head and the profile must be between 0.1-1.00mm, so I used a 0.5mm feeler gauge to set the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20131011-130102.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different view of the final installation. I find that the magnetic tape and encoder gives a very clean and tight installation. It avoids the extensive angle bracket and mounting on the side of the mill base, and it employes the mill table as a natural chip shield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magnetic tape is impervious to coolant and chips, and the encoder head itself is protected to IP67 so in principal, a chip shield is not necessary. However, I think that chips could easily get stuck in the tight clearance between the encoder head and profile holding the magnetic tape, and so I believe that a chip shield is still necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20131011-133749.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is what the full thing looks like :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/project-sx3-dro/20131011-133812.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Awesome Video From A Modern Day Blacksmith</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/10/10/awesome-video-from-a-modern-day-blacksmith"/>
   <updated>2013-10-10T08:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/10/10/awesome-video-from-a-modern-day-blacksmith</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I usually don&amp;#39;t subscribe to Youtube channels. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/user/AweMeChannel/videos?view=0&quot;&gt;AWE me&lt;/a&gt; is one of the rare exceptions, and the only reason is to track the truly amazing creations from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/name/nm1044149/&quot;&gt;Tony Swatton&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.swordandstone.com/the-show&quot;&gt;Sword and the Stone&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every week he posts a video showing the creation of a sword. The videos are short (&amp;lt; 10min), concise, and of great quality being produced by a professional production company. The videos are not  detailed walkthroughs of the processes involved. Rather they are motion picture presentations of the creation with much emphasis on the entertainment value. Which is wholly fine with me. Definitely worth my precious time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The craftsmanship, quality, and attention to detail that is shown is truly amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/yEwne-IEG9s?color=white&amp;theme=light&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Excellent Article On How Photographic Lenses Are Manufactured</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/10/07/how-photographic-lenses-are-manufactured"/>
   <updated>2013-10-07T08:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/10/07/how-photographic-lenses-are-manufactured</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve always been very fond of detailed and illustrated descriptions of how different manufacturing processes work. The show &lt;a href=&quot;http://science.discovery.com/tv-shows/how-its-made&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;How It&amp;#39;s Made&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; has always been a favourite of mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being very interested in photography, I read a lot of photo related web sites, and came across &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imaging-resource.com/news/2013/09/19/a-geeks-tour-of-sigmas-aizu-lens-factory-precision-production-from-the-insi&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; excellent article on Imaging Resource on how photographic lenses are made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It provides a good commentary with a lots of excellent close-ups of the complex machinery involved in the mostly automated manufacturing processes to produce the lenses that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sigmaphoto.com/&quot;&gt;Sigma&lt;/a&gt; sells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This manufacturing process is interesting, in that it also involves machining glass. Most articles and Youtube videos , etc., are about machining different kinds of metals so the challenges involved in machining glass is a nice addition. Take a look at this grinder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2013-10-07/grinder_550px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;grinder&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(credit: Imaging Ressource)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>An Improved Pellet Trap (part 2)&#58; Design</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/10/05/pellet-trap-part2"/>
   <updated>2013-10-05T08:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/10/05/pellet-trap-part2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Previous Posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2013/09/19/pellet-trap-part1&quot;&gt;Part 1, Reasoning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of the pellet trap I&amp;#39;m building is fairly simple, using a combination of friction and impact to stop pellets. First, a replaceable layer of 3mm PVC plastic will use friction to decelerate the pellets, and then two layers of 12mm polyurethane (PUR) sheet will use impact to stop the pellets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m fairly happy with this design, as it meets most of my design goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#39;s low maintenance. The PVC sheet will need replacing from time to time, but not too often. The PUR sheet  should last a very very long time, especially when using wad cutters at no more than 12J.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#39;s quiet. The impact with the PVC sheet will be audible, but much less so than most other materials like wood, hard plastic, or steel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#39;s cheap. Only small amounts of PVC and PUR sheet is required, and the cost per m2 of these materials is low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one property of the design that I&amp;#39;m not too happy about is, that PVC and PUR sheet is fairly difficult to come by in the small quantities required - and whole reel of PVC does cost a lot of money. Patches of conveyer belt can work just as well as PUR, so depending on your geographical location, this may be easier to come by. I have yet to find an alternative to PVC. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main advantages of PVC is that it heals (closes) really well and that no material is &amp;quot;removed&amp;quot; on pellet strike. No other materials I&amp;#39;ve looked at close anywhere near as good and they leave a big mess. Common materials used such as patches of carpet, news paper, phonebooks, and cloth, they don&amp;#39;t &amp;quot;close&amp;quot; the whole after a pellet strikes (carpet and cloth does to a limited extent) and over time they make a mess from the trace materials they leave on pellet strike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullet traps in general are based on one of three principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Impact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Friction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deceleration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impact and friction designs are much simpler than a deceleration design, and maybe as a consequence, no commercially sold pellet trap is based on this design. A pellet carry much less energy than a bullet fired from a firearm, and is thus much easier to stop, which also detracts from using a deceleration design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the inherent &amp;quot;klang&amp;quot; from a pellet trap based on an impact design, I decided the design also needed to incorporate a friction element, to reduce the energy of the final impact strike. With a deceleration design, there will still be a pellet strike, and probably also a &amp;quot;klang&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people are reporting that the &amp;quot;klang&amp;quot; from most pellet traps can effectively be suppressed using some form of moderator (cloth, foam, insulation, etc.), however there is still the risk of lead dust to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friction style bullet traps, in general, are typically based on one of the following designs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sand berm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rubber berm (same as sand berm, but using rubber granule)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sheets of material&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sand berm is a fantastic engineering solution. Cheap, very effective, and &amp;quot;self-reorganizing&amp;quot; so it overcomes the inherent problem of concentrated high energy impacts. Use of rubber granule was inspired by the sand berm. A material was needed that had the same properties as sand, but made separating material from bullets easier. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Action Target has made a very good analysis of berms made from rubber granule (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.actiontarget.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/Myths-About-Rubber-Bullet-Traps.pdf&quot;&gt;original link&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;/files/2013-09-21-pellet-trap-part2/Myths-About-Rubber-Bullet-Traps.pdf&quot;&gt;local copy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US Army also did an extensive study on commercially sold bullet traps, and it&amp;#39;s an excellent walkthrough of different design principles and the associated pros and cons. Here&amp;#39;s the (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.dk/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=5&amp;amp;ved=0CEwQFjAE&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.dtic.mil%2Fcgi-bin%2FGetTRDoc%3FAD%3DADA308438&amp;amp;ei=91c9UqrwBImI4AT5mYHoCg&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNEHWoDjVvsbwOO2pzbwEGPjMAk7HA&amp;amp;sig2=TdUHBCYaFxj8JhLfPKHSdw&amp;amp;bvm=bv.52434380,d.bGE&quot;&gt;original link through Google&lt;/a&gt;) as well as &lt;a href=&quot;/files/2013-09-21-pellet-trap-part2/ADA308438.pdf&quot;&gt;local copy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>An Improved Pellet Trap (part 1)&#58; Reasoning</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/09/19/pellet-trap-part1"/>
   <updated>2013-09-19T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/09/19/pellet-trap-part1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I recently needed an airgun pellet trap for practicing concentration and trigger pull indoors, I expected that a Google search would make quick work of a workable solution. Not so!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had devised a list of functional- and non-functional requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Functional requirements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pellet sizes: 4,5mm (0.177) and 5,5mm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pellet shapes: Flat and domed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pellet energy design envelope: &amp;lt; 16J (12FPE)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pellet energy safety envelope: &amp;lt; 50J&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expected range: 0-10m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-functional requirements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can be used indoors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quiet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free of lead dust&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small, light, and portable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to clean spent pellets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low maintenance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cheap in use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pellet trap poses an interesting engineering challenge: Absorbing thousands of concentrated high energy impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An angled steel plate is a seemingly perfect solution: Simple, cheap, effective, easy to make. Unfortunately, it produces lead dust at impact speeds surpassing 200m/s, so indoor use really is limited to low power air guns. And, even worse, there is that never ending &amp;quot;klang&amp;quot; on pellet impact. That significantly reduces the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wife_acceptance_factor&quot;&gt;WAF factor&lt;/a&gt; :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another, maybe even more seemingly perfect solution, has been devised: The sand berm. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to all the qualities of the angled steel plate, it&amp;#39;s a beatiful engineering solution to the problem of absorbing concentrated impacts: It self organizes. Unfortunately, a sand berm takes up a lot of room. It doesn&amp;#39;t take a lot to stop an airgun pellet, but to have an acceptable height, it needs to be big. An then there&amp;#39;s the whole mess of having it indoors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It quickly became apparent, that all pellet traps being sold are in some way based on an angled steel plate, and so a different solution had to be sought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The go-to solution for an improved pellet trap seems to be variations on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.archerairguns.com/Premium-Silent-Pellet-Trap-p/aapeltrpnoputty.htm&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Silent&amp;quot; Pellet Trap&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to being simple, effective, and easy to make, it&amp;#39;s also quiet and free of lead dust. It seems perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the magic ingreedient in that solution - Duct Seal -  is far from cheap in Denmark where I live. The 6kg which a pellet trap with duct seal typically requires, is almost $200 here :-(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, instead I decided to build an improved pellet trap that would satisfy my requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dial Indicator</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/09/18/dial-indicator"/>
   <updated>2013-09-18T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2013/09/18/dial-indicator</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A dial test indicator is used for so many things, that listing them all doesn&amp;#39;t make sense. For example, accurately squaring your milling vice without one is next to impossible. And starting around  €25 it&amp;#39;s one of the first accessories you should buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cheap Chinese versions are typically sold in a kit with a magnetic stand. Do get such a kit, because it&amp;#39;s cheap and because the stand is nice to have for other things. But instead of using the dial test indicator with the magnetic stand, get an Indicol holder and mount it in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2013-09-18-dial-indicator/20130918-200000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indicol holder makes it easy to attach the dial test indicator to just about any tool holder mounted in the mill spindle, and this arrangement is by far the best way to square a milling vice to the table and tram the mill column. Those two applications alone, make the Indicol holder worth getting, but it has numerous other uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#39;s cheap! Just €15 ($20) for the Indicol holder, which really makes me wonder why there are no kits including one of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dial test indicators have a swivel lever arm, whereas a dial indicator has a plunge lever. I find more different uses for the dial test indicator and so my recommendation would be to get one of those before you get a dial indicator. However, in setups they are interchangeable and so personal preference comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An excellent resource for everything related to dial indicators is &lt;a href=&quot;http://longislandindicator.com/&quot;&gt;Long Island Indicator Service&lt;/a&gt; that specialize in servicing [quality] dial indicators. Dial indicators are high precision mechanical instruments that need maintenance, and the high cost warrant repairs rather than replacements. Their focus is obviously on quality indicators, and not the cheap Chinese tools, but they have a lot of good information, and since a &amp;quot;quality&amp;quot; dial test indicator starts at €130 ($170), it&amp;#39;s one of the accessories where many will opt for the &amp;quot;real thing&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Simple Color Response Test (Method & Results)</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/07/14/simple-color-response-test"/>
   <updated>2010-07-14T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/07/14/simple-color-response-test</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m researching application of white LED&amp;#39;s as a replacement for interior lightning, and as part of that I need to answer two qualitative parameters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many lumens of LED light is needed to replace an 11W CFL bulb and a 20W halogen spot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the color response of LED&amp;#39;s acceptable (and where isn&amp;#39;t it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This small test is my initial effort to address the latter. This test has three purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrate the viability of the testing method&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indication of color response for two different white LED&amp;#39;s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indication of color response for fluorescent tubes and CFL bulb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a background in computer science and electrical engineering, I have no theoretical foundation to base my tests on, and the perception of color response is very subjective (just look at some of the threads on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.candlepowerforums.com/&quot;&gt;Candlepowerforums&lt;/a&gt;). The purpose of this test is not to give authoritative statements on applicability of specific lighting technologies, but to find something I like to look at every day. I&amp;#39;ve always favored cold color temperatures - even halogen light appears yellow to me, and warm white CFL appears greenish - and that, I suspect, will strongly influence my preference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An additional area I also want to investigate is whether a mix of cold and warm white LED&amp;#39;s produce better color response, and if so a rough indication of the ratio of emitters. I realize that mixing red emitters with cold white emitters is probably a better strategy, but my red emitters are still on their way from Hong Kong, so that test will have to wait. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Testing Method&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The test was conducted by placing an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.targets.coloraid.de/&quot;&gt;IT8.7/2&lt;/a&gt; target in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lightbox&quot;&gt;light box&lt;/a&gt; with the light source on left side of the light box. The camera was mounted on a tripod. Shutter speed was kept constant and an aperture was selected according to the light source. The camera white balance was set to 6300K, and shots were recorded in both jpg and raw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this test I used a reflective IT8.7 target printed on Kodak professional paper, because I had trouble fitting the bigger non-reflective A4 version in my light box. This really isn&amp;#39;t ideal, as that IT8.7 is intended for flatbed scanners, not cameras. This would be relevant if I was to use the results to create a color response correction profile for the camera and/or light source, but in this application I don&amp;#39;t think it makes a difference. The brain does a ton psychological &amp;quot;processing&amp;quot; anyway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The target of this test was a cheap superflux LED (brand and type unknown) I&amp;#39;ve sourced in England. I expect them to perform much worse than a quality high power emitter from e.g. Cree or Seoul. For the LED light I wired 3x18 of the superflux LED&amp;#39;s (2x18 cold white and 1x18 warm white), allowing ratios of 1:1 and 2:1 between cold white and warm white.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Post Processing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this test, image post processing was done on the jpg&amp;#39;s in Google Picasa. I&amp;#39;ll redo the post processing in GIMP in a more controlled fashion on the RAW versions when time permits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two post processing steps were done:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Images were cropped to show just the IT8 target&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neutral point was set to the neutral grey reference on the IT8 target, to correct for difference in color temp between the light sources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t really know what selecting neutral point in Picasa actually does. Picasa simplifies everything so it might do some further processing I&amp;#39;m now aware about (hence the need to repeat in GIMP to make sure), but judging by the results it does what I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The processed images are the results: Select which one you like the most. For each image I&amp;#39;ve provided a link to the non temperature corrected version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#39;t quite decided on a satisfactory explanation for the corrected color response of #1 and #2. If I didn&amp;#39;t now otherwise, I&amp;#39;d have expected #1 to be from the warm white LED, but it&amp;#39;s not! I&amp;#39;ve redone the test several times to make sure, and my results can easily be verified by using the non-corrected copy of the image where the color temperature of the warm white emitter is very visible. Anyone care to comment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-07-14-simple-color-response-test/20100714-200001.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;20100602-233520 CW&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20100602-233520 CW&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superflux LED, cold white
Brand and type unknown
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Specifications&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Emitting Color: White
&lt;br/&gt;
Intensity (mcd): 2000-3000
&lt;br/&gt;
Viewing Angle (deg): 100
&lt;br/&gt;
Forward Voltage (V): 3.0-3.6
&lt;br/&gt;
Forward Current (mA): 20-30
&lt;/p&gt;

Purchased &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phenoptix.com/shop/ultra-bright-white-superflux-piranha-leds-3000mcd-p-90.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-07-14-simple-color-response-test/20100714-200002.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;20100602-233620 WW&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20100602-233620 WW&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Superflux LED, warm white
Brand and type unknown
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Specifications&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Emitting Color: Warm White
&lt;br/&gt;
Intensity (mcd): 1800-2500
&lt;br/&gt;
Viewing Angle (deg): 100
&lt;br/&gt;
Forward Voltage (V): 3.0-3.3
&lt;br/&gt;
Forward Current (mA): 20-30
&lt;/p&gt;

Purchased &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phenoptix.com/shop/ultra-bright-white-superflux-piranha-leds-3000mcd-p-90.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-07-14-simple-color-response-test/20100714-200003.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;20100602-233706 CW:WW 1:1&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20100602-233706 CW:WW 1:1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mix of #1 and #2. Ratio cold white to warm white is 1:1&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-07-14-simple-color-response-test/20100714-200004.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;20100602-233746 CW:WW 2:1&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20100602-233746 CW:WW 2:1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mix of #1 and #2. Ratio cold white to warm white is 2:1&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-07-14-simple-color-response-test/20100714-200005.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;2x56W Philips T8 940 Fluorescent tubes&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2x56W Philips T8 940 Fluorescent tubes&lt;br/&gt;
Cold white
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
2x32W No-name T8 840 Fluorescent tubes&lt;br/&gt;
Cold White
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thick white line is the lower left area is glare from the fluorescent tubes, because the color reference is on glossy paper, and there was direct line of sight to one tube mounted in the ceiling.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;   
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-07-14-simple-color-response-test/20100714-200006.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; alt=&quot;20100602-234239 WW CFL&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
&lt;p&gt;20100602-234239 WW CFL&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Cheap no-name low energy bulb&lt;br/&gt;
Warm white
&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Z-axis Bellows Mount (Part 3)&#58; Bottom Bracket</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/06/18/zaxis-bellows-mount-part3"/>
   <updated>2010-06-18T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/06/18/zaxis-bellows-mount-part3</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Previous Posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2010/05/09/started-work-on-a-zaxis-bellows-mount&quot;&gt;Started Work On A Z-axis Bellows Mount&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2010/05/11/zaxis-bellows-mount-part1&quot;&gt;Part 1, Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2010/05/18/zaxis-bellows-mount-part2&quot;&gt;Part 2, Top Bracket&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Bottom Bracket&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made the bottom bracket from a single piece of aluminum measuring 75x235x15mm. In this a slot for the Z-axis way is cut and holes are drilled in the bottom for press fitting the magnets that will fix the bracket to the mill base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting a piece 240mm long from existing bar stock. Even with a brand new bi-metal blade and plenty of WD-40 that is still quite a chore. Time to start saving for that band saw!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-06-18-zaxis-bellows-mount-part3/20100618-230000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squaring the edges of the sawed of piece. Another downside to using a manual hack saw is that the saw cut tends to be quite at quite an angle from vertical, hence the need to remove a lot of material before the edge is square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I&amp;#39;m using a 10mm 4-flute end mill where the end is damaged. It&amp;#39;s certainly not ideal for this type of operation, but squaring ends is purely for cosmetic reasons - the finish and dimensions of the edges are in no way critical - so I decided to save the wear on my other end mills for more critical applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-06-18-zaxis-bellows-mount-part3/20100618-230001.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In part 4, I&amp;#39;ll cover making the bottom bracket ...&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Simple Color Response Test</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/06/14/simple-color-response-test"/>
   <updated>2010-06-14T03:08:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/06/14/simple-color-response-test</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This had been on my todo list for a long time. A comparison of the color response of different light sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incandescent light bulbs have a color rendering index (CRI) of 100 whereas most artificial light sources have a CRI of 70-80, and even &amp;quot;high CRI&amp;quot; versions of artificial light sources only reach CRI values of 90-95. I&amp;#39;m making LED fixtures for a number of lamps around the house, and so I have been interested in finding out what the lower CRI values actually means in terms of color response,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used an IT8 target as my reference. An IT8 target, is a color reference used to calibrate the color profiles of digital imaging equipment such as digital cameras and scanners. The sensors and optical filters in digital imaging equipment is more sensitive to certain colors, and so a calibrated color reference photo is used to compensate for this non-linearity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This characteristic of color imaging equipment is very much similar to the behaviour of artificial light sources that often emit much more light at certain wave lengths (as does fluorescent tubes) or certain bands of wave lengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-06-14-simple-color-response-test/20100602-233746.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Vertex VA-4 Finally Arrived</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/05/20/vertex-va4-Finally-Arrived"/>
   <updated>2010-05-20T01:47:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/05/20/vertex-va4-Finally-Arrived</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever since the SX3 arrived, I&amp;#39;ve been wanting a real milling vice. My 80mm screwless precision vice (something like &lt;a href=&quot;/images/2010-05-19-vertex-va4-Finally-Arrived/20100520-090800.jpg&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;) is adequate for small stuff, but chatter is a significant problem with it, and it shows on the finish. I&amp;#39;ve spent a lot of time searching the Internet for the best one I could afford, a finally decided on the Vertex VA-4. I&amp;#39;ve written more about the selection process here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VA-4 is much more massive than my precision vice and at 20kg vs 6kg for the precision vice it&amp;#39;s a completely different weight class. I really need to make a side-by-side comparison picture to show the true difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The make and finish of the VA-4 is very nice for a Chinese knock-off (the &amp;quot;real deal&amp;quot; is a 4&amp;quot; Kurt angle-lock vice). Finish is much greater than what I&amp;#39;ve seen for other Chinese Kurt-style vices, but it&amp;#39;s not on par with the make and finish of my screwless precision vice. My own general rule for machine tools is that you pay a standard price per kg with the actual price per kg depending on the overall quality, and at 4x the weight but only twice the cost of my screwless vice the VA-4 should be about half as nice in make and finish, and that seems about right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-05-19-vertex-va4-Finally-Arrived/20100520-084500.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Z-axis Bellows Mount (Part 2)&#58; Top Bracket</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/05/18/zaxis-bellows-mount-part2"/>
   <updated>2010-05-18T22:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/05/18/zaxis-bellows-mount-part2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Previous Posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2010/05/09/started-work-on-a-zaxis-bellows-mount&quot;&gt;Started Work On A Z-axis Bellows Mount&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2010/05/11/zaxis-bellows-mount-part1&quot;&gt;Part 1, Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Top Bracket&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top bracket is made of two pieces of aluminum. A smaller bar that holds three magnets, and fixes to the milling head between the tilting head mount and the vertical column, and a wider plate screwed to this bar and to which the top part of the bellows is attached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First step in making the small part of the top bracket is to cut a piece of aluminum 20x15x140mm. I used 6082 but any alloy will do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Layout scribe marks for drilling the holes for the magnets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the right mark is off center from the other two marks to make room for the bottom screw securing the z-axis gib. Also, a small recess for the screw head has been milled in the top right corner of the aluminum bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-05-18-zaxis-bellows-mount-part2/20100518-230000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drilling holes for the magnets in the small bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magnets are round measuring 10mm in diameter and 10mm in length. They will be press fitted in the top bar so the holes are drilled using a 9,9mm drill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finish and hole concentricity doesn&amp;#39;t really matter in this case, so I didn&amp;#39;t bother center drilling or gradually opening up the hole size. I drilled directly to size using plenty of WD-40. The downside to this approach, as can be seen in the image, is the tangle of aluminum swarf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The max spindle speed of the SX3 is 1800rpm which is not nearly enough to break the chips in drilling operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-05-18-zaxis-bellows-mount-part2/20100518-230001.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finished piece that will hold the magnets in the top bracket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each magnet yields a 6,5kg pull, and it remains to be seen if this is adequate to keep the bracket in place when the bellows is fully extended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-05-18-zaxis-bellows-mount-part2/20100518-230002.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2010/06/18/zaxis-bellows-mount-part3&quot;&gt;In part 3, I&amp;#39;ll cover making the bottom bracket ...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What Tolerances Can You Expect</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/05/12/what-tolerances-can-you-expect"/>
   <updated>2010-05-12T16:06:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/05/12/what-tolerances-can-you-expect</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;That was probably the most pressing question I wanted answered, when I got a mill. And the answer seems to be 0,01mm if your very careful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the accuracy of the mill itself - I felt very sure, that straight out of the crate, the mill would be way out of tram, and that certainly was the case! Rather, given a properly trammed mill, to what tolerances should I be able to machine stuff? Give and take how many tenths, hundreds or thousandths of a millimeter should I reliably be able to produce a part of a certain length, width, or height?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the answer was pretty straight forward. Commonly available - and affordable - measuring instruments (calipers, micrometers, height gauges) have a resolution of 0,01mm (digital micrometers and some dial indicators resolve to 0,001mm) and with a repeatability of about 0,03mm - so the answer is at least close to those numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other part of the answer was found in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnccookbook.com/CCMetrologyTooling.html&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; very excellent categorization over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnccookbook.com/&quot;&gt;CNCCookbook&lt;/a&gt; of which measurement instruments are usable when working towards different tolerances, and his personal notes on what tolerances he can achieve on his IH mill (a very nice RF-45 clone) given 10 years of experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Straight out of the crate, the column of my SX3 was 0,6mm out of tram over a range of 250mm side-to-side. My target for tramming the column is 0,01mm over 150mm.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Z-axis Bellows Mount (Part 1)&#58; Introduction</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/05/11/zaxis-bellows-mount-part1"/>
   <updated>2010-05-11T20:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/05/11/zaxis-bellows-mount-part1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Previous Posts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2010/05/09/started-work-on-a-zaxis-bellows-mount&quot;&gt;Started Work On A Z-axis Bellows Mount&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Milling operations generate a lot of swarf, that tend to get into every possible nook and cranny. The Sieg SX3 is a great machine for what it is, but at that price point there are many compromises and omissions, and one of them is proper swarf protection, especially for the ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, most everyone owing a Sieg mini mill and other Chinese benchtop mills end up devising a number of guards and covers to keep swarf from getting into table ways and other unwanted places. My initial approach was a simple Plexiglas shield to keep swarf away from the table and ways. This helped quite a lot, but I decided that something more was needed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-05-11-zaxis-bellows-mount-part1/20100511-230000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part was a bellows cover for the Z-axis mounted using two custom aluminum brackets and 8 rare-earth magnets to keep everything in place. By using magnets for non-critical applications like a bellows mount I avoid drilling and tapping any unnecessary wholes in the mill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Google Sketchup drawing I used for the design is attached. I ended up making many minor corrections that weren&amp;#39;t brought back into the drawings, but these were mostly to improve the overall fit. The drawings will work as-is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Cost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project ended up costing $60. Cheap quality bellows like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arceurotrade.co.uk/Catalogue/Machine-Spares/Machine-Bellows/Concertina-Bellows-300mm-x-200mm---Dip-Moulded-Rubber-084-030-00300&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; can be had for just $10, but I decided that since this would become a permanent part of the machine, I wanted a nicer solution. Overlapping metal way covers are the ideal solution, but that project is pretty involved, so instead I opted for a better quality bellow. Since I live in Europe my options are pretty limited, but Arc Euro Trade carries a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arceurotrade.co.uk/Catalogue/Machine-Spares/Machine-Bellows/Concertina-Bellows-240mm-x-50mm---Laminated-Fabric-084-030-00100&quot;&gt;nice version&lt;/a&gt; that is almost tailor made for the Z-axis way on the SX3. It does, however, cost nearly $40. Add another $10 for the magnets and $10 for the three pieces of aluminum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2010/05/18/zaxis-bellows-mount-part2&quot;&gt;In part 2, I&amp;#39;ll cover making the top bracket ...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Started Work On A Z-axis Bellows Mount</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/05/09/started-work-on-a-zaxis-bellows-mount"/>
   <updated>2010-05-09T14:12:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/05/09/started-work-on-a-zaxis-bellows-mount</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Milling operations generate a lot of swarf, and cleaning up gets old really fast, so I&amp;#39;ve started a project to mount a bellows on the Z-axis of the Sieg SX3 mill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IMHO bellows are an ideal swarf protection for the Z-axis. The mounting areas - mill head and base - are well defined and accessible, mounting a bellows doesn&amp;#39;t limit range of travel, and fully closed there is still enough of the ways exposed to &amp;quot;guide&amp;quot; the bellows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-05-09-started-work-on-a-zaxis-bellows-mount/20100509-141200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2010/05/11/zaxis-bellows-mount-part1&quot;&gt;In part 1, I&amp;#39;ll cover the practical design ...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Clamp For Milling Vice</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/04/01/clamp-for-milling-vice"/>
   <updated>2010-04-01T16:12:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/04/01/clamp-for-milling-vice</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A small clamp I designed for a typical Chinese style &amp;quot;precision milling vise&amp;quot;. It&amp;#39;s designed to be machined from a 40mm length of 25mm square tool steel rod, and is fixed using an M10 hex cap screw. The original Google Sketchup file is &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/files/2010-04-01-clamp-for-milling-vice/milling-vice-clamp.skp&quot;&gt;attached&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-04-01-clamp-for-milling-vice/20100401-141200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Choosing A Mill</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/03/27/choosing-a-mill"/>
   <updated>2010-03-27T11:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/03/27/choosing-a-mill</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just got a Sieg SX3, but it was no easy decision. Choosing your first vertical mill is a difficult decision you&amp;#39;ll probably end up spending weeks and countless hours researching on the Internet. This describes the selection process I went through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Before You Start Looking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I needed to make up my mind about three things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What tasks must it absolutely be able to perform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the range of your budget&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What size machinery can I successfully install in my basement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What Will You Actually Do With It?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you make do with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sherline.com/&quot;&gt;Sherline&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.taigtools.com/&quot;&gt;Taig&lt;/a&gt;, or do you need something bigger? The quality and finishing of Sherline and Taig mills is great, but their small size significantly limits what size of projects can comfortably be completed, and you don&amp;#39;t want to always work near the upper limit of the machine&amp;#39;s work envelope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly realized, I had tons of things I really would like to do on a vertical mill, and I hesitantly accepted that I probably wouldn&amp;#39;t be able to do half of them on a mill I could actually afford. However, there are many other reasons why I will probably never be able to complete those projects: lack of time, cost of materials, insufficient electrical installations [for the required machine], unable to get the machine into my basement, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The type of material you want to machine is imho less important. Everybody wants to take deep, fast, and clean cuts in stainless steel, but I don&amp;#39;t think even a Bridgeport size machine will do some of the stuff you can see on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=cnc+milling+stainless+steel&amp;amp;search_type=&amp;amp;aq=1m&quot;&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;. All vertical mills handle wood, plastics, and aluminum quite easily, so it really comes down to the size of the things to be machined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I decided, that I mostly work on things that are too large to fit in a Sherline size mill, and so I need something bigger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Price!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people only care about if a certain tool or piece of equipment will perform the task at hand - and some people really enjoy using the very best tool that will perform the task at hand. I&amp;#39;m very much one of the latter: I enjoy quality tools just for the sake of their quality, and I select accordingly. If possible, I select and buy tools that are at least one &amp;quot;class&amp;quot; better than what is actually need, and this strategy has payed off many times - and many times not :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t believe in setting a fixed price as an upper limit for how much to spend: Another $100 may make a huge difference, and the added cost of a more expensive machine can be offset by postponing purchases of additional tooling. On the other hand, tooling make things possible that would otherwise not have been, and so I quickly discovered that within days of getting my mill, the total price tag of my tooling-wish-list far surpassed the cost of the mill itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I set out to by a new piece of tool, I often end up with something about twice as expensive as what I originally had in mind, and that also ended up being the case with the mill, but the market for vertical mills, although growing, is still very small and consequently the available offerings are comparatively few - an living outside the US, they are an order of magnitude fewer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of actual budget, it means that a budget of $500-2.000 will buy pretty much any model that weighs less than 200kg, and there&amp;#39;s generally a proportional relationship between weight and cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How Big Can It Actually Be?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a sanity check. Ever tried moving a 165kg piece of somewhat fragile machinery?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before getting a Sieg SX3 I hadn&amp;#39;t, and it proved to be quite a task. I knew in advance that I wouldn&amp;#39;t be able to get it down into my basement in one piece: That&amp;#39;s not possible without a crane which I don&amp;#39;t have and nor do I have the room to operate a crane to get the Sieg SX3 into my basement. That meant taking the thing apart (I can highly recommend this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arceurotrade.co.uk/projects/prepguides/X3%20Mill%20Preparation%20Guide.pdf&quot;&gt;guide&lt;/a&gt; by Arc Euro Trade) which is a project in itself, and even so the &amp;quot;big pieces&amp;quot; were still 40kg and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottom line, unless you have a way to move &amp;gt;100kg machinery into position or is willing to take the thing apart, go for a smaller model. I can dream about an RF45 clone, but getting it into place would be a nightmare!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;New vs Used&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve read a lot of forums threads where people ask which vertical mill to get, or if so and so [cheap Chinese import] mill is any good. Invariably, some seasoned machinist will point out that the same money can buy an old used mill that is much better. While the &amp;quot;much better&amp;quot; part of that argument seems true, I find the realities to be less clear cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I&amp;#39;ve yet to find an old used mill that can be had for the same money as a large Chinese benchtop size vertical mill. Almost all old used mills I&amp;#39;ve found, have cost at least three times more than a new large Chinese benchtop mill. The few I&amp;#39;ve found that cost only twice as much, were so covered in rust, that they would require countless hours of tender loving care to function properly. However, 2 or 3 times the price of a Chinese benchtop mill is way beyond my budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, an old used mill is enormous compared to a Chinese benchtop mill. Of course that&amp;#39;s a major advantage, but it&amp;#39;s also a major impediment: There&amp;#39;s no way I&amp;#39;m getting that size of machinery into my basement (and if size isn&amp;#39;t an issue, then the weight of at least 500-800kg definitely is). Unless you have a large ground level garage to put it in, and old used mill really isn&amp;#39;t a tenable solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, an old used mill is expensive and difficult to service and maintain. Spares for such a beast, if they are even available, are very expensive - some parts will easily cost more than a new Chinese benchtop mill :-) That means making the parts yourself, which takes significant time and skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I&amp;#39;ve noted that there are remarkably few used Chinese benchtop mills on sale given the considerable popularity these have gained over the past 10 years, so hopefully that means people are too happy with them to sell them. However, this may just be because I live in Denmark where the market for Chinese machine tools is generally non-existent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, a cheap Chinese benchtop mill was my only viable alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Chinese Origin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s important to realize that pretty much all benchtop size mills that cost less that $3.000 are manufactured by one of two Chinese companies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.siegind.com/&quot;&gt;Sieg Industries&lt;/a&gt; (maker of X1, X2, X3, etc. models), and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.weiss.com.cn/&quot;&gt;Weiss Machinery&lt;/a&gt; (maker of BF16, BF20, etc. models).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two notable exceptions I know of, are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sherline.com/&quot;&gt;Sherline&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.taigtools.com/&quot;&gt;Taig&lt;/a&gt;, and if their small size is not a limiting factor then I would recommend them over similar size Chinese manufactured mills (they do however cost twice as much).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sieg have been most popular in the US (sold through Harbor Freight and Grizzly), whereas Weiss have been more popular in Europe (either Weiss branded or through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.optimum-machines.com/&quot;&gt;Optimum Machines&lt;/a&gt;), but this seems to be changing and Grizzly now also carries e.g. the BF20 (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hossmachine.info/&quot;&gt;Hossmachine&lt;/a&gt; has a nice &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hossmachine.info/G0704.html&quot;&gt;comparison&lt;/a&gt; of the models from the different manufacturers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Which One?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have $10k to spend, just buy a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wabeco-remscheid.de/&quot;&gt;Wabeco F1410 LF HS&lt;/a&gt;, and be done with it :-)  If you &amp;quot;only&amp;quot; have $5k to spend, and a way to move a 250kg piece of machinery into position, get a nice RF-45 clone. For the rest of us, a different approach is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially it seemed quite easy. Just get the best within the budget, and bigger is almost always better, pretty much regardless of dimension. However, the sub $3.000 vertical mills start at about $500 and then get incrementally better and more expensive and so I ended up going through a long winded &amp;quot;trade off&amp;quot; process e.g. is another $200 better spend on a 4&amp;quot; milling vice (tooling), or a slightly large mill table (better mill). I ended up listing all relevant models in a spreadsheet (web view &lt;a href=&quot;http://spreadsheets.google.com/pub?key=ppNonvjfydGmjC_YE4vloSA&amp;amp;single=true&amp;amp;gid=0&amp;amp;output=html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) to get a better overview, and I included models that were cheaper, and models that were more expensive than what I hoped for, if they for some reason seemed relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t actually make any of those artificial trade offs, but it helped me understand what my two &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; and hard requirements were: Proven design and belt drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Proven Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve read a lot of negative comments about Chinese made machine tools, and most comments either relate to sub-standard finishing or flawed design. I decided that I can deal with sub-standard finishing either by accepting or by improving it myself, but a flawed design is difficult to compensate for. I&amp;#39;m no expert on machine construction so my only way to avoid a flawed design was to get a mill of a proven design, which means a mill that&amp;#39;s been in production a long time and has a lot of users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sieg models fit this description. They&amp;#39;ve been in production for 10 years, have been continually improved, and they have a lot of happy users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Belt Drive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is less obvious. I actually have two reasons why this is important to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first reason is practical: I only get to use the mill at night when my  two young children have gone to bed. Keeping the noise volume down is imperative, and gears make a LOT of noise, which makes them undesirable. I don&amp;#39;t think the noise level from a gear driven mill would actually have been a problem, but it&amp;#39;s nice not having to worry about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason is about enjoyment and a relates to the proven design. I wanted to be reasonably happy with the mill as delivered, and I wouldn&amp;#39;t have been fully happy with a gear driven Sieg X1 or X2 until I had converted it to belt drive. Small Chinese mills use plastic gears and they break, easily! There are untold stories of users, who&amp;#39;ve stripped the gears in their Sieg X1 and X2 models. Getting a replacement gear wheel in Denmark is next to impossible, and easily costs $30. So it sums up to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;#39;t want to have to spend the time doing a belt drive conversion. Workshop time is quite a premium for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;#39;t want to have to worry about or deal with broken plastic gears (again, workshop time is a premium).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting a LittleMachineShop Sieg X2 belt drive conversion kit is very expensive when ordering from Denmark (shipping, import taxes, Danish VAT, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, I needed belt drive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Selection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might argue that the hard &amp;quot;belt drive&amp;quot; requirement doesn&amp;#39;t offer any actual choice, but Sieg had just introducet the SX2 (an X2 with upgraded motor, and belt drive) when I started looking, so at least I had a choice between two models, the Sieg SX3 being the only other model with belt drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very tempted by the Sieg SX2, but I always felt a table depth of 95mm just wasn&amp;#39;t enough and it was quite unclear when it would actually become available. On top of that the Sieg SX3 just seemed sooo much better, and it&amp;#39;s work envelope was much closer to what I was hoping for, and so that&amp;#39;s what I ended up with.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Sieg SX3 Has Arrived...</title>
   <link href="http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/03/26/the-sieg-sx3-has-arrived"/>
   <updated>2010-03-26T22:47:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://diy.strandbygaard.net/2010/03/26/the-sieg-sx3-has-arrived</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2010-03-26-the-sieg-sx3-has-arrived/20100326-230000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>